Nicole: So, what motivates
bad and good actors?
Abraham: Bad Actors or threat actors
have malicious intent and are constantly
looking for ways to infiltrate an
organisations networks and systems.
Nicole: Cyber criminals or black hat
hackers are the most common threat
actors, and their aim is to exploit
human security vulnerabilities.
Attacks may involve hacking into devices
to gain password details and stealing
or making data inaccessible to an
organisation by holding it to ransom.
Financial gain is usually the motive,
and their weapons of choice are often
phishing attacks, ransomware, and malware.
Abraham: Hacktivists are activist
groups or collectives who instead of
being motivated by purely financial
or personal gain, carry out 'attacks'
in support of ideological or political
causes and may target industries or
specific organisations, who don't
share their political views or causes.
By disrupting organisations,
they feel that they can alert the
media and public to their cause,
but they do it by criminal means.
One of the most well-known Hactivist
groups is Anonymous, known for their cyber
attacks on governments, corporations,
and the Church of Scientology.
Nicole: Not only do threat
actors come from outside of an
organisation they also exist within.
They may be former or current employees
who attempt to exploit vulnerabilities
using ransomware, malware and
hacking tools but with legitimate
access to networks and systems.
Their motivation may be financial,
but it may also be for espionage
reasons or sabotage, or even just
for revenge, to get their own back,
especially if they have been dismissed.
Abraham: And then there are those who are
motivated by personal reasons, just to
have fun, create chaos or seek attention.
These are threat actors known as
script kiddies, and are able to do a
lot of damage, just because they can!
Nicole: So, what about good
actors or white hat hackers?
Are they bad actors who
have seen the light?
For some this is actually true!
Check out Kevin Mitnick, who was
arrested in 1995 for black hat activities
by the FBI, now a trusted security
consultant with his own security company.
Abraham: To know how to make
systems cyber secure and thwart
the hackers, cybersecurity
professionals must first think like
a hacker, then act like a hacker.
But the difference is this is all done
with the permission and authorisation
of the system owner, in order to beat
the cyber criminals at their own game.
They use all the tools a black
hat hacker would use but their
motivation is to be a force for good.
Nicole: White hat hackers
or ethical hackers come in
a range of different forms.
They perform roles of security
experts and analysts, penetration
testers and cybersecurity researchers.
But their motivations are not just
about doing good, they can also
make a good living out of being
a white hat hacker or good actor.
Afterall saving an organisation money by
improving its security can be worth a lot!